so I have a few questions about
Consciousness is vigana consciousness
does that equal awareness right no the
answer is no it
doesn't um you can be you can choose to
be aware and you can choose well you
could be unaware or distracted either
way you are
conscious so awareness is only possible
because you're already conscious
so if a person starts to uh look at
their experience and they haven't come across
experience and they haven't come across
Buddhism
or any other spiritual teaching and they
say what is happening here MH there here
is a I'm I'm feeling something mhm I'm
perceiving things you know visual things
sounds smells tastes touches mhm I'm
having thoughts
I have desires
intentions wishes yeah and I have a so
that's I have a a body you know to some
extent they they see that understand
that and I'm aware of my situation I'm
aware of these things I know it and I
can pay attention here and there so okay
how would they wouldn't necessarily come
up with this idea of consciousness
like how do you see that that because
you can be aware of all these components
yeah well that's the that's the thing
like um you cannot be aware of your
um you cannot be aware of your
Consciousness directly you cannot be
conscious of your Consciousness that's a
contradiction in terms so how would you
know that it even is such a thing the
the purification that the sutas would be
describing purification of your
intention purification of greed aversion
delusion removal of those things from
your assumption from your intentions
from your
choices that's what develops your
awareness your selfawareness
selfawareness of your situation and this
passion that comes from it and that's
why through the practicing of
purification of this
passion Consciousness will be fully
understood how the Su to say it
Consciousness is to be fully understood
so you don't understand it by sort of
making an object of it in you're
thinking because obviously that won't be
the Consciousness Consciousness is kind of
Consciousness Consciousness is kind of
it's on the level where the where the
form is where the perceptions are like
on their own so to speak it's not
something you
do so the fact that you as I said the
fact that you can be aware that you can
intend this or that means your conscious
form is already
there and any attempt to access or or
get to or see directly that
Consciousness part of that exper of the
five Aggregates or experience the whole
you not you're not going to be seeing
the Consciousness that's why only
through fully developing this passion
towards form towards feelings towards
perceptions towards intentions what
you're left with removed the passion
will be removed from that as well and
that will be the full understanding of
the five
Aggregates so that's another thing
whether you try to understand
Consciousness or or try to understand
your feelings or try to understand your
intentions or try to understand the form
it can only be done on the basis of
inseparable five
Aggregates you cannot be thinking just
the Consciousness or thinking just the
feeling whenever you single one of those
all five the experience as a whole is
already
there so person needs to recognize that
because obviously your views and
assumptions can be kind of
implying and and um hoping that you
could figure out or access or see or
perceive the pure consciousness of it
that's why any view that revolves around
the ideas of pure Consciousness is a
contradiction in terms all you're going
to have doesn't matter how subtle how uh
coar how unfamiliar how familiar how uh
big or small expensive or shrunk
experience you might have it's the
experience of the five Aggregates how
fleeting how slow it's the five
Aggregates that that's all you can have
and any single aspect of the five
Aggregates that you pick up with your
attention with your assumptions it's the
five Aggregates again so it's five
within the five within the five within
the five it doesn't matter what
direction you
go so first and foremost you have to
stop thinking about Consciousness as
some sort of entity that exists there to
which things appear see those are your
images those are your mental images your
mental thoughts the the Damas the
phenomena that appear because you're
already conscious because your form is
there not bereft of
Consciousness so that's why it's the
only way as it s say to fully understand
the Consciousness is to become an outand
in other words the only way to fully
understand the Consciousness is to be
completely free from Passion completely
free from ill will completely overcome
the hindrances everything else is going
to come short it's is going to be
carrying one assumption or the other one
gratuitous standpoint or the
other so how far can we go with our
understanding without being arance then
so even though we can short you you go
as far as you practice the disp rightly
you don't go as far through thinking and
pondering and proliferating about your
ideas of consciousness
so the there's to me it just sounds like
there is a living
body say you take these terms living
body dead body living body is the
conscious body and so to me it sounds like that
body and so to me it sounds like that
living part is what the what we
constitute as the well colloquially yes
you could say that but again you cannot
step outside of the Living Part to see
the full picture which means that's
going to be a gratuitous Point placed at
it that's limiting your
perspective yeah it's
the the ultimate negative is it's the
ultimate negative it's think about it's
the ultimate opposite end of the spectrum of
ultimate opposite end of the spectrum of
the five
Aggregates any standpoint in regard to
the five Aggregates that you take well
you're going to be obscuring some part
of that Spectrum the only way to have
the entire Spectrum unobscured is to
completely fully remove the slightest
traces of appropriation and passion
towards it doesn't matter whether it's the
it doesn't matter whether it's the
cautious forms or the subtlest most
refined most Sublime most most abstract
experiences it's the five Aggregates and
there is no part of it anywhere that you
are still holding on to so complete
dispassion that's why you don't really
care if the Consciousness is
um Supply LI or if if your awareness is
just uh awareness of light and mystical
experiences devoid of form it doesn't
matter it's only relatively devoid of
form because even the mental experiences
are the experiences of the five
Aggregates even the physical experiences
are the experience of the Consciousness
spectrum of things even the coarsest
physical experience of complete
unawareness Consciousness still there so that's what
Consciousness still there so that's what
I mean they're Inseparable the five
heaps are
inseparable and for as long as you're
trying to find or think that
understanding of the Aggregates pertains
to the content of a specific Aggregates
here now or now and then or at some
point or experiencing specific types of
feeling uh developing specific types of
Perceptions in and of themselves finding
the real uh pure uh unpolluted
Consciousness is the way out no it's
still the five Aggregates so doesn't
matter what mystical idea or scientific
idea you might have it's still the five
Aggregates the only way to fully have
the spectrum of the five Aggregates that
is unin interfered with through Gru's
appropriation and so on is to remove
passion uh aversion and distraction in
regard to it and that's the full
understanding that's the fully developed
sort speak understanding of
Consciousness ey of the whole thing of
the five Aggregates there is nothing
held back or obscured or hidden as a
basis for your ownership your sense of
self your conceit and everything else
but what's what's nice about what you're
saying there is
that uh because you hear full
understanding of Consciousness you need
to have that you be an Arun so let me
get the information yeah about it and
let me figure it out and then well
there's no problem in getting the
information the problem is what
information I get yeah and how far can
you understand yeah CU people CU see
that's see if if uh you can be getting
information and you need to be getting
information and you need to you need to
even begin by getting the abstract
information like you know what the
difference is where to look for
Consciousness just to give you some idea
to wrap your head around but the bottom
line is it will have to boil down to are
you actually practicing or just trying
to figure it out on account of your
fully corrupted five Aggregates and
you're not doing anything about the
Corruptions you're not doing anything
about the limitations of your
perspective just on on top of it you're
trying to
piece everything together and get a and
get a perspective ultimate perspective
and then you might start to practice
when everything is clear and that's
never going to happen because EXA it's
always going to be a limited
standpoint something is always going to
be left out if you're coming from that
standpoint of I can see the Spectrum I
can perceive the
Consciousness I can step outside of the
five Aggregates and measure them or or
basically imply a measure through
thinking you're observing them
impartially objectively as if failing to
understand that you're objectively
observing something is your subjective
experience of the five Aggregates so you
cannot step outside of it as we said so
many times you know well mention the
sutas even like when people remember the
previous lives and stuff uh when the S
talk about it says they all all they
remember is the five upgrades or one
specific among them among the group
right in particular yeah you're
completely enclosed yeah the wholesome s
is the five agates what maybe is more
more important is to get that
uh okay obviously remove all dispassion
for the Aggregates not develop dision
sorry develop dision for the
AGG uh but to to know how enclosed you
are to get a feel for that that
understanding yeah rather than well
that's closer that's closer
closer that's closer
to understanding Consciousness even if
you don't think in terms of I'm
understanding Consciousness because that
is that is the your direct experience in
a way that is that is the least
proliferated yeah uh perspective from
what your experience actually is yeah
it's the least corrupted even if you
haven't fully understood the five
aggregates through nonproliferation of
greed aversion distraction you are
closer to seeing it how it is so to
speak yeah it's you are enclosed by the
situation yeah thinking these things are
not yours you're undermined by all these
things and
each do and that's unability of it an just
do and that's unability of it an just
getting that uh feeling is it or that
tone of think getting that message
getting that perspec that perspective
sink in rather than loads of information
about it but just that you're
approaching to that external point of
view as I often say yeah externalizing
you think that you're thinking thinks
outside of the five Aggregates and
trying to as I said piece it together
from this external standpoint failing to
understand that your objective external
standpoint is your subjective experience
yeah at that given time which means
there is no outside of it so while
you're trying to figure out that
Consciousness and so on you you're kind
of missing you're not seeing from the
actual perspective that you are you are
overlooking the domain where the
practice is that's why I say like just
even keeping the precepts in the
beginning when you start you start by
keeping the precepts and purifying your
course Behavior that's already doing the
same thing that's already preventing you
from maintaining the behavior that
carries a belief that you are outside of
your senses outside inside of your sense
bases the whole like attraction or
aversion to sense objects carries an
implicit view that they're outside of my
sense Fields yet the only way to
experience sights is Through Your Eyes
seeing things so you are perceiving your
eyes seeing things you're not perceiving
things which is people do they develop a
view that I'm perceiving things and they
forget about their eyes I'm tasting
tastes they forget about the the the
mouth same with the body I'm perceiving
Sensations they forget about the the the
the form the matter they are necessary
for those perceptions they Overlook the
sense
basis so all you can perceive is Your
Body perceiving Sensations all you can
hear is your ears hearing sounds you
can't step outside of it and access the
sounds directly it's uncon it's
inconceivable but that implication is
cared not that you not not because you
actually at some point experien things
outside of your senses no it's simply
because you've been ignoring your sense
bases I the the the the body the
experience as a whole here and now
you've been ignoring it for so long that
it's invisible so all you see is sense
objects so all that it feels like I'm
not like a person might think I'm not
having an external view of myself I
don't ever think like that are you
attracted to sense objects are you
repelled by sense objects there's
already an external view to your five
aggregates so that's why you can
philosophize and theorize all you want
if you're not developing The Virtue in
that right sense of Discerning the
intention behind your actions whether
they're rooted in greed or non- greed
aversion or non aversion distraction or
non- distraction and cultivating that
you will never then come back on the
level of the five Aggregates doesn't
matter how much you think about them
doesn't matter what meditation
experiences you you might think you have
um that's all just within the five
aggrades that are being overlooked
within the six sense Fields sense bases
Salat as it should say they're the
completely invisible all you see sense
objects so even when people then
perceive these sense
objects if they have kind of if they
like in regard to my own body for
example like Sensations and stuff
they'll think oh these are the internal
these are the sense sense spaces it's
like no they're again doesn't matter how
internal your Sensations might feel they
perceived anything that it's perceived
it's on account of as I said existing
sense bases that are
overlooked underneath you invisible
behind you wherever invisible invisible
because as I said you U uh perception of
these external counterparts sense
objects sight sound smell taste
sensations those
perceptions through overlooking the
internal basis carry the assumption that
that's outside of you
so even if you're perceiving things
seemingly inside the only reason it
feels inside is because you're so far
outside that's in your assumption that
something that's less outside feels like
inside but if you were to stop
proliferating and feeding such behaviors
through keeping the virtue sense
restraint uh recognizing the
responsibility behind your actions by
Body speech and Mind by by by senses by
engaging with eyes and so on um you are
bringing that that line of what's
internal what's external closer and
closer and closer you seeing what's
underneath well what's underneath
becomes uh sort
of
outlined the behind becomes outlined
yeah the sense bases the counterparts
the the other side of the spectrum it's
sort of becoming peripherally outlined
you're becoming aware of it that's like
developing the signs of the Mind the
whole thing it's exactly the same the
same practice so so yeah that's the
point I'm trying to like emphasize here
is
that more often than not a person will
think I don't have an external view of
my situation I don't carry that
view but you that person or whoever
thinks that needs to
recognize that that whether you think
you're carrying the view or
not is not the measure of the view what
the measure is is are you
withdrawn from engaging with sense
objects are you withdrawn from acting
out of ill will are you withdrawn from
basically acting out of the five
hindrances if
not the only reason that you are still
able to be affected by the five
hindrances still act out of greed
aversion still act out of desires is
because you are still carrying an
external view you are still implying it
maybe not as much as before and that
external view being just to be clear
that I am outside well that I can be
that at least part of my experience as a
whole of the five Aggregates is outside
of this
situation that's how it that's how it
feels yes you could say that yeah so
when people practice watching the
sensations it feels like oh this is
underneath of this experience as a whole
when people chase sensual objects out
there in the world it feels like they're
outside of me over there and I'm getting
them through engaging with them failing
to understand that even a mere
possibility of going toward sense
objects or going internally toward
Sensations it's only possible because
the sense
Fields the Salat is already there
perceiving those things perceiving those
possibilities enabling
them like they're already conscious is
the conscious eye yeah and the the the
the only thing you can access is the
conscious eye
seeing forms the conscious Ear hearing
sounds the conscious
Body perceiving
Sensations even the conscious mind
thinking thoughts you can't access the
thoughts either no more that you can
access SES
yet all of those
things s sound smell tast touches
thoughts or S sound smell taste
sensations thoughts feel like they're
external to your point of view they come
from out there arm
here and that's because there's still
traces or a lot not just traces of
overlooking seeing
past the Salat the six sense
fears or the experience as a whole or
the five grades whichever you describe
it in its in its right extent in its
entire Spectrum which is includes that
peripheral perception because you can't
look at it
directly so for as long as there is that
perception is obscured through passion
aversion distraction there will be a degree of my
distraction there will be a degree of my
point of view and everything else
outside of it in other words there will
be a degree of conceit only arant is
truly completely thoroughly free from
conceit from the the standpoint